MINGZE WANG

210, Jingyuan Building #6, Peking University, Beijing, China, 100084 mingzewang@stu.pku.edu.cn

SHORT BIO

I am a third-year Ph.D student in Computational Mathematics, Peking University. I am very fortunate to be advised by Prof. Weinan E. Prior to that, I received my B.S. degree in Pure and Applied Mathematics (ranking 1/111 for the first three years during my undergraduate study) from Zhejiang University in 2021. My homepage is https://wmz9.github.io/.

EDUCATION

Peking University

Beijing, China

Ph.D Candidate, Computational Mathematics

2021.09 - Present

School of Mathematical Sciences

Advisor: Prof. Weinan E.

Zhejiang University

Hangzhou, China

Bachelor of Science, Pure and Applied Mathematics

2017.09 - 2021.06

School of Mathematical Sciences

Academic ranking: 1/111, Comprehensive ranking: 1/111, Major GPA: 4.84/5 (95.5/100).

EXPERIENCE

Peking University

Beijing, China

Teaching assistant: Deep Learning Theory, taught by Prof. Zhiyuan Li

Summer School 2023.

Teaching assistant: Calculus (A)

Fall 2021

Teaching assistant: Calculus (B)

Fall 2022, 2023; Spring 2022, 2023, 2024

Institute for Advanced Algorithms Research

Algorithm Intern

Shanghai, China

2023.12 - now

Work on designing faster optimizers for pretraining large language models.

Mogi Technology

Beijing, China

Algorithm Intern

2021.09 - 2022.06

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am broadly interested in theory, algorithm and application of machine learning. I am also interested in non-convex and convex optimization. Recently, I am also dedicated to to use theory to design algorithms elegantly. Specifically, my recent research topics are

- Deep learning theory: optimization, generalization, implicit bias, and approximation. [1][2][3][4][5][6][7][8][10][11]
 - **Optimization**: When training neural networks, why can optimization algorithms converge to global minima? [1][4]
 - **Implicit Bias**: When training neural networks, why can optimization algorithms converge to global minima with favorable generalization ability (even without any explicit regularization)? Such as flat-minima-bias [2][5] and max-margin-bias aspects [4][6].
 - Algorithm Design: For machine learning problems, design new optimization algorithms which can converge to global minima with better generalization ability. [6] (On the preparation)
 - Approximation: Exploring the expressive power of deep neural networks through the lens of approximation theory. [7]
 - Generalization: How to measure the generalization ability of neural networks. [3]
- Foundation Model and Transformer: theory and algorithm. [7][10][11]

- **Expressive Power**: The expressive power and mechanisms of Transformer [7]; the theory of in-context learning [11]
- Algorithm Design: Designing faster optimizers for pretraining LLMs. [10]
- Non-convex and Convex Optimization: theory and algorithm. [1][4][6][10]
 - Convex Optimization in ML. [6]
 - Non-convex Optimization in ML. [1][4][10]
 - Algorithm Design: For deep neural networks, design new optimization algorithms to achieve faster training. [10]
- CV and NLP: algorithm and application [9][10].

PUBLICATIONS & PREPRINTS

- [1] Mingze Wang, Chao Ma. Early Stage Convergence and Global Convergence of Training Mildly Parameterized Neural Networks. (73 pages) Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2022). 2022.
- [2] Lei Wu, Mingze Wang, Weijie J. Su. The alignment property of SGD noise and how it helps select flat minima: A stability analysis. (25 pages) Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2022). 2022.
- [3] Mingze Wang, Chao Ma. Generalization Error Bounds for Deep Neural Networks Trained by SGD. (32 pages) Under review. arXiv preprint: 2206.03299, 2022.
- [4] Mingze Wang, Chao Ma. Understanding Multi-phase Optimization Dynamics and Rich Non-linear Behaviors of ReLU Networks. (94 pages) Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2023, Spotlight (Top 3.5%)). 2023.
- [5] Mingze Wang, Lei Wu. A Theoretical Analysis of Noise Geometry in Stochastic Gradient Descent. (30 pages) NeurIPS 2023 Workshop on Mathematics of Modern Machine Learning (NeurIPS 2023 Workshop M3L). arXiv preprint: 2310.00692, 2023.
- [6] Mingze Wang, Zeping Min, Lei Wu. Achieving Margin Maximization Exponentially Fast via Progressive Norm Rescaling. (38 pages) International Conference on Machine Learning, (ICML 2024) 2023.
- [7] Mingze Wang, Weinan E. Understanding the Expressive Power and Mechanisms of Transformer for Sequence Modeling. (70 pages) arXiv preprint: 2402.00522, 2024.
- [8] Liu Ziyin, Mingze Wang, Hongchao Li, Lei Wu. The Implicit Bias of Gradient Noise: a Symmetry Perspective. (17 pages) arXiv preprint: 2402.07193, 2024.
- [9] Guanhua Huang, Yuchen Zhang, Zhe Li, Yongjian You, Mingze Wang, Zhouwang Yang. Are Al-Generated Text Detectors Robust to Adversarial Perturbations? Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, (ACL 2024). 2024.
- [10] Mingze Wang, Haotian He, Jinbo Wang, Zilin Wang, Guanhua Huang, Feiyu Xiong, Zhiyu Li, Weinan E, Lei Wu. Improving Generalization and Convergence by Enhancing Implicit Regularization. (35 pages) arXiv preprint: 2405.20763, 2024.

SERVICE

Conference: Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS); International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR).

Journal: Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR); Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI); Pattern Recognition (PR); Journal of Machine Learning (JML).

SELECTED AWARDS & HONOURS

Principal Scholarship, Peking University.	2024.05
BICMR Mathematical Award for Graduate Students (top 1%, 110,000 RMB), Peking University.	2023.11
Schlumberge Scholarship (30,000 RMB), Peking University.	2022.10
PKU Academic Innovation Award (top 1%), Peking University.	2022.10
Outstanding Graduate of Zhejiang Province (top 5%)	2021.05
Outstanding Graduate of ZJU	2021.05
Chinese National Scholarship (top 1%)	2019.10
First Class Scholarship of ZJU (top 3%)	2019, 2020.10
Zhejiang Provincial Government Scholarship	2018.10
First Prize of Mathematical Contest in Modeling of ZJU (top 1%)	2020.06
Meritourious Award in The Mathematical Contest in Modeling	2020.02
National Second Prize of Chinese Undergraduate Mathematical Contest in Modeling (top 2.5%)	2019.10

SELECTED UNDERGRADUATE TRANSCRIPT

Real Analysis	100	Functional Analysis	100	Partial Differential Equation	100
Scientific Computing	100	Mathematical Analysis (II)	99	Differential Geometry	99
Point Topology	99	Mathematical Physics	97	Complex Analysis	97
Calculus (I)	97	Stochastic Process	96	Foundation of Analysis	96